<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An answer to all the excuses and pretences which men ordinarily make for their not coming to the Holy Communion ... by a divine of the Church of England.</title>
            <author>Synge, Edward, 1659-1741.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1697</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 45 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 19 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A62123</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S6375</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R1735</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12627591</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12627591</idno>
            <idno type="VID">64680</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A62123)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 64680)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 336:9)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An answer to all the excuses and pretences which men ordinarily make for their not coming to the Holy Communion ... by a divine of the Church of England.</title>
                  <author>Synge, Edward, 1659-1741.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <editionStmt>
                  <edition>The second edition corrected.</edition>
               </editionStmt>
               <extent>36 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Richard Sare ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1697.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to Edward Synge. Cf. BM.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Lord's Supper --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:64680:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:64680:1"/>
            <p> AN ANSWER TO ALL THE EXCUSES AND PRETENCES Which Men ordinarily make for their not coming to the HOLY COMMUNION.</p>
            <p>Fitted for the Meaneſt Capacities, And very proper to be given away by ſuch as are Charitably Inclined. Price 3 pence.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By a Divine of the Church of</hi> England.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Second Edition Corrected.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>Richard Sare,</hi> at <hi>Gray's-Inn-Gate;</hi> in <hi>Holborn.</hi> 1697.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:64680:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:64680:2"/>
            <head>AN ANSWER TO All the <hi>Excuſes</hi> and <hi>Pretences</hi> which Men ordinarily make for their not coming to the Holy COMMUNION.</head>
            <p>A <hi>Certain man made a</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Luk. 6. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>great Supper and bad many; And ſent his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant at Supper time, to ſay to them that were <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>idden, Come, for all things are now rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y. And they all with one conſent began <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>O MAKE EXC<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>SE:</hi> &amp;c. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he deſign of this Parable is to repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>nt the manner of Gods dealing with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e people of the Jews, upon their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>cting the Faith of Chriſt and refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:64680:3"/> to embrace the Goſpel. The A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles of Chriſt, who were the Servants of God, were ſent and commanded, in the firſt place, to Preach the glad ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings of the Goſpel to them; and to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vite them to come, and partake of that Bleſſing and Happineſs, which was offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them by God, through Faith in, and Obedience unto, his Son Chriſt <hi>Jeſus.</hi> But they, generally, having their hearts, wholly in a manner addicted to the Love of this World; had no inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to receive ſo pure and Spiritual an Inſtitution; and did not only them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves reject, but alſo perſecuted others for embracing, the Chriſtian Profeſſion; deſpiſing and <hi>treading under foot the Son of God, and counting the Blood of the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant,</hi> wherewith they ſhould have been <hi>Sanctified, an unholy thing; and</hi> even <hi>do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing deſpight unto the Spirit of Grace,</hi> which would have wrought upon their hearts in order to their Converſion. As there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Man in this Parable, who made the Supper, was offended with thoſe who did not come when they were In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vited; and therefore wholly Excluded them from his Table; and ſent his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant to call others in their room (as you may find it in the latter part of
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:64680:3"/> it:) So did Almighty God caſt off the People of the Jews, upon their ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinate rejecting of <hi>Jeſus</hi> Chriſt; gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving them up to be deſtroyed and ſcat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered by the power of the Romans; And commanded the Apoſtles to go out into all parts of the World, to gather a Church, and a peculiar People, unto him from among the Gentiles. But my preſent aim in Reflecting upon this Parable, lies clear Another way; namely, to repreſent, and reprove, thoſe <hi>Excuſes</hi> and <hi>Pretences,</hi> which ſo many men do make, for their groſs neglect of the <hi>Holy Communion of the Body and Blood of Chriſt</hi> notwithſtanding that God, by the Mouth of his Miniſters, does ſo frequently call, and earneſtly invite them thereunto. And indeed this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter is, in ſo lively a manner, repreſented in the whole deſign of it that I think it is ſcarce poſſible to draw a more ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>act Parallel.</p>
            <p>For here, In the firſt place, we have Almighty God making a Supper for us; for the feeding and nouriſhing of our Souls, in Vertue and Piety, through the Paſſion, and Death, of our Saviour Chriſt <hi>Jeſus,</hi> which he has appointed for ever to be commemorated by our
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:64680:4"/> Eating of this Bread and Drinking of this Cup, in Remembrance of him. To this Supper we are, not once only, but, often, bidden; by the frequent Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monitions and Exhortations of God's Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters addreſſed unto us, that we ſhould come and be partakers of this Holy Communion: And as the Gueſts who were invited in this Parable had framed ſome weak, and impertinent excuſes, for their not coming; One had <hi>bought a piece of Ground,</hi> another <hi>five Yoke of Oxen,</hi> and a third had <hi>Married a Wife;</hi> none of which things needed to have hinder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them from accepting of the good man's kindneſs. Juſt ſo we, when from Month to Month, and from Year to Year, we continually turn our backs upon God's Holy Table; have yet ſome ſort of pretences wherewith we endeavour to ſatisfie our Conſciences, and to excuſe this groſs and ſcandalous neglect of which we are Guilty.</p>
            <p>That our Saviour Chriſt <hi>Jeſus</hi> died for our Sins; that it is only for the ſake of his Merits and Sufferings, that we can hope for Pardon and Eternal Life at the hand of God; That, before his Death, he left this command with all that ſhould be called by his Name, that
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:64680:4"/> they ſhould <hi>Eat of this Bread, and Drink of this Cup, in remembrance of him;</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by we are obliged to ſhew forth his Death untill his ſecond coming: And laſtly, that this ordinance is the <hi>Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion</hi> of the <hi>Body</hi> and <hi>Blood of Chriſt;</hi> or, in other terms, the means whereby we do Communicate in the Benefits of that Sacrifice, which Chriſt offered, and in the merits of that Death and Paſſion, which he underwent in his <hi>Body,</hi> and by the ſheding of his <hi>Blood</hi> for us; and, conſequently, that the Receiving here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, if duly performed, is not only our duty but alſo a great advantage and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit unto us; All theſe things, I ſay, are ſo univerſally owned by all who profeſs Chriſtianity, that I need not offer any thing for the proof of them, or any part of them. But then ſurely one would think that when men, who are thus perſwaded, do ſo often, and for ſo long a time, abſent themſelves from this ordinance, there muſt be ſome inſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perable difficulties, and obſtacles in their way, which it is beyond their ſtrength or power to remove; or elſe that they would never, at the ſame time, both neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect their Duty, and forego their Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt. And yet I doubt not but to make
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:64680:5"/> it appear, as plainly as any thing can be, that there is nothing which we can, at any time, pretend as a hinderance of our coming to the Holy Communion; but what either is really, or ought to be, no hinderance at all; or elſe is ſuch as it is in our power, by that grace and aſſiſtance which God never denies to thoſe who ſeek it, wholly to remove and put out of the way.</p>
            <p>To come to the matter then, and that I may proceed in an orderly me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod; I ſhall reduce all the impediments, which men do ever alledge for their not coming unto the holy Communion, to theſe Five heads: that is to ſay, either, <hi>Firſt,</hi> that they are Sinners, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore dare not come; or <hi>Secondly,</hi> that they are ſo continually engaged, and ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken up with Buſineſs, that they have not time to prepare themſelves for it; or, <hi>Thirdly,</hi> that when they do endeavour to prepare themſelves, they find they cannot do it as it ought to be done; or, <hi>Fourthly,</hi> that having formerly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived the Communion, they find them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves never the better for it, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore think it to no purpoſe to come a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain; or, <hi>Laſtly,</hi> that they are not well ſatisfied with the manner of Celebra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:64680:5"/> Adminiſtring, and Receiving this Ordinance in our Church, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore cannot joyn with our Congregati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in it: Nor is there, I think, any thing that can be urged by way of Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe for not coming to the Holy Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion, but what I ſhall fairly examine, and I hope effectually confute, under ſome one or other of theſe Particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars.</p>
            <p>1. Then, ſome Men may ſay, that they are great Sinners, and therefore, upon that account, dare not come to the Holy Communion, for fear leaſt they ſhould be unworthy Receivers, and ſo, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of obtaining any Benefit thereby, ſhould only <hi>Eat and Drink their own Damnation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To this I anſwer, that if a Man lies under the guilt of any Sin, and does not repent of it, and Heartily reſolve to forſake and amend it; it is indeed a Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption and a Sin for ſuch a Perſon, whileſt he continues in that ſtate, to come to the Communion. But then I muſt tell him alſo, that not only his coming to the Holy Communion, but even his very <hi>Prayers</hi> are an <hi>Abomination</hi> to God <hi>Prov.</hi> 28. 9. For what is it elſe but a perfect Affront, and even a Mocking of
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:64680:6"/> the Divine Majeſty, for a man to make a ſhew of Worſhip and Honour to him, whileſt, at the ſame time, he goes on in willful diſobedience to his known com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands? Which I wiſh were well and ſeriouſly conſidered by thoſe men, who make no ſcruple of addreſſing themſelves to God in Prayer, whileſt, by reaſon of their ſins, of which they have not repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, they dare not approach unto his Holy Table.</p>
            <p>But whatever ſins a Man has been Guilty of in times paſt, if he truly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pents of them, and Heartily forſakes them for the time to come; God has, ſo often and ſo plainly, promiſed in this caſe to grant a full and free Pardon of them, that they cannot juſtly be pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed as any obſtacle, which ſhould hinder us from approaching to him in any of his Ordinances.</p>
            <p>Since then it is in the Power of every Man (at leaſt of every one who by a long courſe of Wickedneſs has not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voked God wholly to withdraw his Grace from him) by that Grace and Aſſiſtance, which God continually offers unto us, to repent of his ſins, and amend his Life: If ſuch a Man looks upon his ſins as a Bar between him and the Holy Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion;
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:64680:6"/> yet it is plainly ſuch a Bar as is in his Power to remove, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore can never juſtly be pleaded as an excuſe in his behalf.</p>
            <p>But ſome man perhaps may ſay, that tho' he ſhould beg God's pardon for his ſins paſt, and ſincerely reſolve to forſake them; yet he fears, that, being frail, he may ſome time or other be prevailed on, by his own weakneſs or the ſtrength of a Temptation, to break thoſe reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutions which he has made, and return again to his ſins. And if this ſhould ever be the caſe with him, he doubts whether God would ever again admit him to Pardon and Reconciliation. And therefore he thinks it ſafer to abſtain from the Holy Communion, rather then to run the hazard of being for ever ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded from the hopes of Heaven.</p>
            <p>In anſwer to this I ſhall offer theſe three things.</p>
            <p>Firſt, Altho' a Man does plainly fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſee, that hereafter he ſhall be moſt like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſometimes to fall into ſome Sins of frail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and infirmity, (ſuch as a haſty Word or a ſuddain and unadviſed Action) yet this ought not to hinder him from com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Holy Communion: For as St. <hi>James</hi> tells us, that, <hi>In many things we</hi>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:64680:7"/> 
               <hi>offend all,</hi> Ja. 3. 2. So is there not any man upon the face of the Earth, who can be Abſolutely ſure that he ſhall alwaies here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after keep himſelf free from all manner of ſin whatſoever. On the contrary as there is no man but what has his ſhare, more or leſs, of human infirmities, ſo is it moſt reaſonable to conclude, that, in the courſe of his Life, theſe will ſometimes unavoidably ſurpriſe and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tray him into ſome Sins. Againſt theſe our Infirmities therefore we muſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually ſtrive: And we may reaſonably hope, that, by God's grace, and our own diligent and careful Endeavours, we may every day more and more prevail againſt them: But if this were a good Reaſon for abſtaining from the Holy Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, becauſe a Man cannot, at once, get a full and perfect Victory over them; I cannot ſee how, even the beſt of men, (who cannot pretend to abſolute per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection) could ſafely venture to par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take of it: And conſequently, this would be the way wholly to lay aſide, and aboliſh the very Ordinance it ſelf.</p>
            <p>Secondly, but as for willful and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liberate Sins, or returning again unto an habitual courſe of wickedneſs; there is no man but, by the grace of God, and
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:64680:7"/> his own endeavours, may, if he pleaſes, for ever ſecure himſelf againſt it. For however God may think it fit, for our greater humility and a farther tryal of us, to leave us ſtill expoſed to ſome of the common infirmities of our Nature; yet, in reſpect of all habitual or deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berate Sins, we may aſſure our ſelves that <hi>he is faithfull,</hi> and <hi>will not ſuffer us to be tempted above that we are able; but will with the temptation alſo make a way to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcape, that we may</hi> (if it be not our own fault) <hi>be able to bear it,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10. 13. Nor will he fail to <hi>draw nigh unto us,</hi> whil'ſt we continue carefull to <hi>draw nigh unto him. Jam.</hi> 4. 8. Let us then but ſtedfaſtly reſolve, that we will be hearty and induſtrious, in doing what lies in our own power; and we need not be diſcouraged by any ſuch fears as theſe, as long as we are ſecure that God will never let us want his aſſiſtance.</p>
            <p>But Thirdly, let us put the caſe as bad as may be; that, after a ſerious Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, and moſt ſtedfaſt Reſolutions of Amendment, ratified and confirmed by the reception of the Holy Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion; a Man ſhould be ſo far prevailed upon by the temptations of the World, the Fleſh, and the Devil, as to return again to his former wickedneſs, in as high or a higher degree than before; Yet even
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:64680:8"/> in this caſe we cannot conclude that ſuch a perſon is forever excluded by God from all poſſibility of pardon and recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciliation. There are indeed ſome paſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of Scripture, that do repreſent the condition of ſuch an one, to be very dreadful and dangerous: As <hi>Heb.</hi> 6. 4, 5. 6. and Chap. 10. 26. 27. 2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. 20. 21. But if, on the other ſide, we conſider how often, and how highly, the Mercy of God is ſet forth and magnified, even towards the greateſt Sinners, upon their true Repentance, that <hi>he has no pleaſure in the Death of the Wicked, but that the Wicked turn from his way and Live.</hi> Ezek. 33. 11. that <hi>he is long-ſuffering to us ward, not willing that any ſhould periſh, but that all ſhould come to Repentance.</hi> 2. Pet. 3. 9. that <hi>tho' our Sins be as Scarlet, or as Red as Crimſon,</hi> yet God is moſt ready, upon our Repentance, to make them <hi>as white as Wooll or Snow.</hi> Iſai. 1. 18. From theſe and many ſuch paſſages of Scripture I think we may well gather, that if the moſt Profligate and Relapſed Sinner, does, even after a long time, come at laſt to ſuch a ſenſe of his own Condition as throughly to <hi>turn from the Wickedneſs that he hath committed,</hi> and to Live the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mainder of his days in the practice of Virtue and good Works, <hi>doing that which is Lawful and right,</hi> and notwithſtanding all
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:64680:8"/> his failures, yet at laſt continues and Perſeveres therein, that even ſuch a Perſon as this <hi>ſhall Save his Soul alive.</hi> Ezek. 18. 27. Altho', at the ſame time, it ſtands with a great deal of Reaſon, that the greater a Man's Sins have been, and the oftner he has relapſed into them, the deeper his Sorrow, and the more la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borious his Repentance muſt be, in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to obtain his Pardon. But ſince a poſſibility of Pardon there is, even in this caſe it ſelf; we muſt not make the contrary fear a pretence for keeping our ſelves back from any of the Ordinances of God, and from a more immediate and intimate Communion with him.</p>
            <p>And thus much for the firſt Impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diment.</p>
            <p>But Secondly ſome men pretend that they are ſo continually engaged, and ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken up with Buſineſs, that they have not time to Prepare themſelves for the Holy Communion, and therefore do not come to it.</p>
            <p>To ſuch men as theſe I anſwer, that this Buſineſs, which they pretend, is ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Lawful buſineſs or Unlawful: If it be Unlawful Buſineſs, and ſuch as cannot be followed with a good Conſcience, it muſt be renounced and wholly laid aſide. And to plead this as a Reaſon for not
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:64680:9"/> coming to the Holy Communion, is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together to aggravate, inſtead of excu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, our neglect. But if the buſineſs be it ſelf Lawful, and followed in a Lawful way; if it neither contains, nor engages us in, any thing, which is diſhoneſt, or any way contrary to the Law of God; ſuch Buſineſs as this is ſo far from un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qualifying a Man, that really it rather renders him the more fit to Receive the Holy Communion. For as Idleneſs is it ſelf a Sin, and the Mother, or at leaſt the Nurſe, of all manner of Wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs; ſo Honeſt and Lawful buſineſs is a Duty which every man is obliged to be diligent in; 1. <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 4. 11. <hi>Eph.</hi> 4. 28. And certainly the performance of a Man's duty will never render him the leſs Acceptable to God, or unfit to draw near unto him in this or any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of his Ordinances.</p>
            <p>But there is one particular ſort of Bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs, in which ſome men think that whil'ſt they are engaged, they cannot be well prepared for the Holy Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion; and that is a Law Suit. But to this the very ſame Anſwer muſt be given that is already returned to the pretence of Buſineſs in general. If a man en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gages in a Suit of Law, with a deſign to wrong, or defraud, another; If in the
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:64680:9"/> management of it he has recourſe to any baſe and Wicked arts or contrivan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces; If, not contented fairly to try the Merit of the cauſe, he ſtrives, by all ways, to caſt Perſonal Reflections upon his Adverſary; or, in a word, if here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in he proceeds in ſuch a way as is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary either to Juſtice or Charity; ſuch a Law Suit as this, I confeſs, renders a man altogether unfit to approach unto God in any way whatſoever; not only whil'ſt he is engaged in it, but alſo un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til he has made Reſtitution, and Satisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, to the beſt of his Power, for all the Wrong which he has thereby done to his Neighbour. But then why will any Man who pretends to Chriſtianity, engage in ſuch a matter as this; which is contrary to common Honeſty and a good Conſcience? Or if Unadviſedly he has engaged himſelf, before he knew what he did; Why does he not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw, and forbear to Proſecute an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt cauſe, or a juſt one in an unjuſt way? Why does he not make Satisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to his Neighbour, if he has done him any Wrong? And how can he think to plead that as an excuſe for not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to Gods Holy Table, which it is in his Power to lay aſide and to Reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy whenever he pleaſes?</p>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:64680:10"/>
            <p> But on the other ſide, if he deſigns no more but Fairly to make uſe of the Law of the Land, and the Power of the Magiſtrate (who is ordained of God) either to Defend, or Recover, what in Conſcience he is verily perſwaded is his juſt and Lawful right; if in the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagement of his Buſineſs he proceeds Honeſtly, and without any Fraud or Jug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle; And laſtly if he bears no Malice, nor offers any way to vent his Spleen againſt the Perſon of his Adverſary, but is always free and ready to do him any rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable Office of Kindneſs or Friendſhip; In ſuch a Law ſuit as this there is nothing which is contrary to the Duty of a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, nor conſequently any thing which needs be, in the leaſt, a Hinderance to his coming to the Holy Communion.</p>
            <p>But ſome perhaps will ſay that altho' there is nothing Sinful or Unlawful either in the Buſineſs they are about, or in their way of managing or follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it; yet their time is ſo wholly ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken up thereby, that they have not lei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure for the Performance of thoſe ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn, and Particular Devotions, which are neceſſary in order to their due Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration. Nay ſuch may be the condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of ſome, that they have not, it may be, ſo much as a place of retirement for
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:64680:10"/> their private Devotions (which may be the caſe of many Servants, and pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Soldiers, and ſuch like) and how can they prepare themſelves as they ought, or how ſhall they venture to come if they are not ſo prepared.</p>
            <p>To this I anſwer, that it is a miſtake, which ſome well meaning Men have en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertained, that they think they muſt not venture to Receive the Holy Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion except they ſay ſo many Prayers, and ſpend ſo many hours in Retirement and Meditation, for ſome days immediatly before the Celebration of it. Where a man indeed is at his own Command, and Maſter of his own time; he is much to be approved of and commended, if, upon ſuch an Occaſion as this, he ſpends more hours, than at other times, in pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Prayer Reading and Meditation; that he may <hi>trim his Lamp</hi> before he goes <hi>to meet the Bridegroom;</hi> and cleanſe and Adorn his <hi>Wedding garment,</hi> before he comes to the Marriage Feaſt. But where the Publick ſervice of a Man's Country, or the Private neceſſities of himſelf or his Family, do engage him in ſo much Buſineſs as that he has not ſuch leiſure for Retirement; If in the mid'ſt of his Affairs, he ever takes care to have God in his thoughts, and often to lift
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:64680:11"/> up his Heart to him by private Ejacula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; and when he has neither Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber nor Cloſet, Garden nor Field, to withdraw himſelf into, if he but ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly retires into his own thoughts (which a Man may do in any place; upon his Bed at midnight, and even in the midſt of the greateſt Croud in the day time) and there enquires into his Paſt Sins, and renews his Reſolutions of Amendment; and if all this proceeds from an <hi>honeſt and well meaning Heart,</hi> truly and affectionately diſpoſed, to the ſervice of God, and the practice of Piety: no doubt but it ſhall be as well ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted by God, as the more ſolemn De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votions of thoſe, who have better op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity for ſuch performances.</p>
            <p>And thus much for the Second Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pediment.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Some pretend that when they do endeavour to prepare themſelves for the Holy Communion, they find they cannot do it as it ought to be done, and therefore they do not come: To the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Scruples of which ſort of Men I ſhall return brief and diſtinct An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers.</p>
            <p>Some then do apprehend, that they are not fit to come, becauſe they are Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, and not well grounded and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:64680:11"/> in the Principles of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
            <p>To this I Anſwer, that, indeed, if a Man be Ignorant of thoſe things which are ordinarily neceſſary to the Salvation of every Chriſtian; it is, evidently not fit that he ſhould come to the Holy Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion, until ſuch time as he be better Inſtructed. But ſuch Inſtruction as this is ſo eaſy to be had (at leaſt amongſt us) that it muſt be every Man's own fault if he wants it. For how eaſy is it for every Man, who either reads the Scripture, or hears it read and Expound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in our Congregations, ſufficiently to learn all the great and neceſſary things of Chriſtian Religion; As for Example, that God Created all things; that <hi>Jeſus</hi> Chriſt is the Son of God, that he came into the World and took our Nature upon him, to Suffer for our Redemption; that, after he had Suffered, he roſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain from the Dead, and Aſcended into Heaven, where he remains for ever in the Glory and Majeſty of God, making Eternal Interceſſion for us; and that he ſhall come again at the end of the World to Judge both the living and the dead; (who ſhall at that time be raiſed again) and to ſentence every man either to Everlaſting Happineſs or Eternal Miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry:
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:64680:12"/> That every Chriſtian is to be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted into the Church by Baptiſm; that it is his Duty to live Soberly, Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſly, and Godly, in this preſent World; and that it is by the aſſiſtance of the Holy Ghoſt, who is the giver of Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual life unto us, that we are alone ena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled to perform theſe Duties. And Laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that, in remembrance of the Death and Paſſion of our Saviour <hi>Jeſus</hi> Chriſt, we are Commanded to Eat of that Bread, and Drink of that Cup, which he has ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed; and which is the Communion of his Body and Blood, that is to ſay, the means whereby we do Communicate in the benefits of the Sacrifice which he offered, and in the merits of his Paſſion, which he underwent in his <hi>Body,</hi> and by the ſheding of his <hi>Blood</hi> for our ſakes, as I have already ſaid. All this, I ſay, is ſo eaſy to be learnt and underſtood, that it is a great ſhame for any one who Lives in a Chriſtian Country to be Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant of any part of it. And he who is thus far Inſtructed in his Religion; and endeavours, according to his ability, to encreaſe his knowledge of Divine things; and hereunto adds the Honeſt and Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere Practice of what he underſtands; needs never fear that God will reject him for want of more knowledge. For
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:64680:12"/> altho' we muſt, according to our Capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city, <hi>add to our Vertue; Knowledge;</hi> yet it is not abundance of Knowledge, but much Honeſty, Charity, and true Piety, that renders us acceptable and Pleaſing to God, ſee 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 1. 19. to the <hi>7th</hi> verſe of the 2<hi>d.</hi> Chapter.</p>
            <p>Again ſome do find their Faith to be weak and wavering; and perplexed with doubts, and Scruples, in matters of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion; and therefore are afraid to come.</p>
            <p>To this I anſwer, that indeed the ſtron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger and Firmer, a Mans Faith is, ſo much the better; and we ought to endeavour, as much as in us lies, that our Faith may ever be built upon ſure and ſolid Principles, as well for our own comfort &amp; ſatisfaction, as that we may be the better able, upon occaſion, to <hi>give an Anſwer to every one who ſhall ask us a Reaſon of the hope that is in us</hi> 1. Pet. 3. 15. But when a Man has done what he can to ſtrengthen and Confirm his Faith, if it ſtill continues Infirm and weak; yet if he be Honeſt and Pious, in his Life and Practice; he is never the leſs acceptable to God for the weakneſs of his Faith. For ſtrength of Faith is not a thing in our own Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer; and therefore not ſo much a Duty in us, as a Reward which God is pleaſed to beſtow, in ſuch a meaſure as he thinks
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:64680:13"/> fit, upon thoſe who are ſincere and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligent in his Service: And <hi>he that is weak in the Faith,</hi> may yet be a very good Chriſtian, and fit to be <hi>Received</hi> into the Church of Chriſt; altho' he be not qualified for <hi>doubtful Diſputations</hi> Ro. 14. 1. As long as a Tree continues to bring forth plenty of Fruit, we are ſure it is alive, nor do we preſently cut it down and caſt it into the Fire, becauſe it is not altogether ſo well fixed at the root, and therefore, it may be ſubject to be ſhaken by the violence of the Wind: And the weakeſt Faith, if it produces a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundance of good Works, ſhall be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted by God; when the ſtrongeſt Faith, if barren and unfruitful, ſhall be rejected and ſet at nought by him. See <hi>Jam.</hi> 2. 14. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Whenever therefore an honeſt and well diſpoſed Man finds his Faith to be any way weak and wavering, let him take up the good Man's ſpeech in the Goſpel <hi>Lord I beleive help thou mine unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief. Mar.</hi> 9. 24. And let him never fear but that God who is infinitely gracious and merciful will accept of him.</p>
            <p>Some, again are afraid that they do not love God as well as they ought; and the reaſon of this fear is, becauſe they do not find in themſelves ſuch warm and affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onate motions of their mind towards him,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:64680:13"/> as they apprehend to be ſuitable to his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite excellency and goodneſs: And for this Reaſon they dare not venture to come.</p>
            <p>To this I anſwer that, indeed, the more ardent and Affectionate our love to God is, ſo much the better is that, as well as our Faith, for being ſtrong and unſhaken. But as our Faith is to be judged of by its fruitfulneſs rather than its Firmneſs (as I have juſt now ſhewn) ſo the Holy Scripture teaches us That <hi>the Love of God</hi> conſiſts altogether in <hi>Keeping his Commandments</hi> 1. Joh. 5. 3. Some people are Naturally of ſuch a temper as more eaſily to be moved with a Paſſionate affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on towards thoſe they Love then others are: And yet others, who do not find ſuch warm Motions within themſelves, may be as ready and willing as they, to do acts of Kindneſs where they profeſs a Friendſhip. Nor is the Love of the later ſort ever the leſs to be Valued, becauſe it appears to be Seated and fixed more in the Judgment and will, which are Subject to leſs altera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, than the Affections: As the true Love of a Wife to her Husband, is to be meaſured by her readineſs to obey and pleaſe him in all things, much rather then by the fond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs which ſhe expreſſes to his Perſon. If therefore a Man finds himſelf ſtedfaſtly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:64680:14"/> 
               <hi>with full purpoſe of Heart, to cleave unto God,</hi> and upon all Occaſions to do what he Commands; ever preferring the pleaſing of him before any, or all, the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours, Profits, or Pleaſures, of this World; he may aſſure himſelf that he is a real and true Lover of God; nor need he abſent himſelf from the Holy Communion, for want of that Ardency and Livelineſs of affection to God, which the very beſt of Men perhaps do oftener wiſh for than enjoy, or find within themſelves.</p>
            <p>Others there are who Fear they are not in perfect Charity with all the World: They have ſometimes had to do with Men of Baſe and Unjuſt dealings, who have broken their promiſes, and, it may be, their Oaths; and thereby betray'd them who have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pended on them; or have otherwiſe been Guilty of wicked and unworthy Practices. And altho', in Obedience to God's com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, they would not do any thing by way of Revenge, even againſt theſe very Men; yet as often as they ſee them, or do but think of them, they find their very Blood to riſe againſt them, and cannot poſſibly Suppreſs that Anger, and Indignation, which ſprings up in their Minds againſt ſuch perſons; and therefore they Fear that their Charity is Defective, and ſo dare not come to the Holy Communion.</p>
            <pb n="27" facs="tcp:64680:14"/>
            <p> To this I anſwer that our Charity to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards Man, as well as our Love to God, is to be Meaſured by the purpoſes and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutions of our will, and our Actions con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequent thereto; and not by the ſuddain Motions of our Paſſions and Affections: Which in the Caſe above mentioned, may be ſcarcely ſo much in our Power, as wholly to be Conquered and ſtifled by us. But whatever Paſſionate reſentments may force themſelves into our minds, upon ſuch oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions as theſe; if we do not ſuffer them to break out into Bitter and Reproachful expreſſions, or Malicious and Revengeful Actions: And if in Spite of our Anger we do firmly reſolve, in Obedience to God's command, to return Good, and not Evil, for Evil: In a word if, as St. <hi>Paul</hi> directs us, when we are <hi>Angry,</hi> we take care and watch over our ſelves that we <hi>Sin not,</hi> Eph. 4. 26. (which is certainly in our Power through the Grace of God &amp; our own Endeavours;) we need not fear that any ſuch inward mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of our Paſſions, as we cannot wholly ſuppreſs, but yet do not ſuffer to break out into any Sinful words or Actions; ſhall ever be imputed to us as a Breach of Charity.</p>
            <p>Others again are afraid that they are not ſorrowful enough for the Sins which they have Commited, becauſe they do not find
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:64680:15"/> their Grief ſo quick and pungent as they think it ought to be; nor ſtrong enough even ſo much as to bring a Tear from their Eyes; and therefore they dare not venture to come.</p>
            <p>To this I anſwer that true it is, indeed, that we can never grieve too much for our Sins, whereby we have offended our good and gracious God: And if even <hi>Rivers of tears</hi> could run down our Eyes, on this occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, they would all be but little enough. But yet, after all; our ſorrow for ſin, is not to be meaſured by the Paſſionateneſs of it, which is ſoon over; or the tears it pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duces, which are as ſoon dried up; but is altogether to be eſtimated by the Amend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment which it cauſes in our Lives. It is a never failing rule which St. <hi>Paul</hi> gives us to know <hi>Godly Sorrow</hi> by, which is, that it <hi>worketh Repentance,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7. 10. If then a Man has ſo true and ſerious a ſenſe of his Sins, as that it brings him to Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, that is to ſay, to a thorough and laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Reformation of his life; this Sorrow, tho' it never affects him in a Paſſionate way, or draws any Tears at all from his Eyes; yet is certainly true godly Sorrow, and ſuch as ſhall be accepted by God; becauſe it worketh Repentance, which is the only End for which godly Sorrow is either required or valued.</p>
            <pb n="29" facs="tcp:64680:15"/>
            <p> Others yet again there are who com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain, that when they would ſet themſelves to prepare for the Holy Communion, they in a little time grow ſo tired with the length of thoſe Devotions which are there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto required, that they are not able to accompliſh what they propos'd. And when they would even <hi>force</hi> themſelves to continue their Prayers and Meditations; they cannot, with all their care, keep their Minds fixed, and attentive, upon what they are about; but their thoughts, will una<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voidably wander upon other things that are Idle and Impertinent. And this they apprehend to be the Sin of <hi>drawing near to God with their Mouths, and Honouring him with their Lips, when their Heart is far from him,</hi> Iſai. 29. 13. And therefore They dare not come unto his Holy Table.</p>
            <p>To this I anſwer, that whenever we ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſs our ſelves unto God in Prayer, we ought certainly to uſe our utmoſt endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour ſo to fix and compoſe our Minds, as that our thoughts may not wander and go aſtray, if we can Poſſibly hinder them.</p>
            <p>And he who pretends to Pray with his Lips, and does not withall ſtrive that his Heart and mind may be Devoutly affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, is undoubtedly Guilty of a great ſlight put upon the Majeſty of God; &amp; may juſtly be taxed with ſome part of that Sin which
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:64680:16"/> I but juſt now made Mention of. But when a Man has done the beſt he can to fix his thoughts, and to keep his mind from wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring in Prayer; If after all this, idle and Impertinent imaginations, do, againſt his will, croud themſelves upon him; and like Flies, tho'continually beaten off, yet ſtill Return again and moleſt him; In this caſe he may well Aſſure himſelf that God who is Gracious and Merciful, will never im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute that to him as a Sin, which, with all his endeavours, he cannot help: But it ſhall only be Reckoned upon the ſcore of his Infirmities, againſt which indeed he muſt ever ſtrive; but it may be ſhall never be able wholly to Conquer them as long as he Lives.</p>
            <p>But there is one piece of advice which I think very proper to offer unto thoſe that are in theſe circumſtances; which is, that they ſhould compriſe their private de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votions in as few words as conveniently they can; and then they will neither be ſo apt to be tired, nor their thoughts to wander therein, as when they are drawn out to a greater length. It is not <hi>much Speaking</hi> that makes our Prayers the more acceptable to God, or the ſooner heard by him, <hi>Mat.</hi> 6. 7. And it is eaſy to compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend all, that is ordinarily neceſſary to be ſaid in Prayer, in a few words. The Lord's Prayer is but ſhort; and yet very full;
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:64680:16"/> and certainly a form moſt acceptable to God. The Publicans <hi>God be merciful to me a Sinner,</hi> Luk. 18. 13. was as well received, coming from a ſincere and honeſt heart, as if he had made his confeſſion in more words. And there is no manner of doubt but that ſhort and devout Ejaculations, frequently offered up to God, by a truly pious Soul, ſhall effectually prevail at the throne of Grace, when they come from ſuch a Perſon, as by Reaſon of his natural frailty and infirmity, is not ſo well able to make longer prayers.</p>
            <p>Again ſome there are who are given to mirth and company keeping; and know not how well to become ſerious, and reſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved enough, to be fit for the Holy Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, and therefore they do not come.</p>
            <p>I anſwer, that a Chearful and Pleaſant Diſpoſition is ſo far from being unlawful, or any way diſpleaſing to God; that, on the contrary, where it is rightly managed, and kept within due bounds, it is common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly very ſerviceable to the promoting of peace and love in the world, which is one of the great ends of Chriſtian Religion. Let then a man but take <hi>ſtrict</hi> care, that his mirth be not ſinful in it's ſelf, nor inſtrumental to promote wickedneſs in the world: Let him not droll upon Religion and piety, nor <hi>make a mock at Sin:</hi> Let no jeſt that is bitter or ſarcaſtical, or tends to
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:64680:17"/> the diſcredit or undervaluing of his Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, or which is any way profane, filthy, or obſcene, come forth of his Lips; nor let him ſhew any manner of delight or ſatisfaction when ſuch things are vented by others: Let him abſtain from all debauched Songs or Stories, which ſeem to be contrived on pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to corrupt the World: And let him never promote, but alwaies, as much as he can, diſcountenance all manner of Rioting, Drunkneſs, Lewdneſs and Profaneſs: In a word, let him be ſure that his mirth be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trays neither himſelf, nor others, to any thing which is contrary to piety, charity or Sobriety; And as long as he keeps himſelf within ſuch bounds as theſe (which is plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly very poſſible to every Man who will heartily reſolve it) he needs not fear that a chearful, and facetious behaviour, will render him ever the the worſe a Chriſtian, or the leſs fit to receive the Holy Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion.</p>
            <p>And laſt of all (that I may conclude what I have to ſay under this Head) ſome there are who, having met with many croſſes and afflictions in the World, have their minds ſo diſcompoſed and their thoughts diſtracted with care, grief, or trouble, that they cannot ſettle their minds, as they think they ought, for the Holy Communion; and therefore they do not come to it.</p>
            <pb n="33" facs="tcp:64680:17"/>
            <p> To this I anſwer, that if any trouble or affliction provokes a Man to Impatience, and prevails ſo far as to make him murmur and repine againſt the providence of God; this, indeed, is a Sin, and muſt, and may, as all other Sins, be repented of, as I have already ſaid under the firſt Head of this Diſcourſe. But if there be no more in it then this, that the croſſes and vexa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions under which a Man lies, do ſo diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compoſe his Mind, as that he can not keep his thoughts from wandering when he is at his Devotion; to this caſe I have but juſt now ſpoken, and need not repeat what I have ſaid upon it.</p>
            <p>And thus I have at laſt done with the Third impediment; upon which I have been forced the longer to dwell, becauſe of the many ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, and objections, which it affords.</p>
            <p>I ſhall need to ſpeak but a word or two, to the Fourth impediment, which ſome Men pretend; namely that, having formerly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived the Holy Communion, they find them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves never the better for it; and therefore think it to no purpoſe to come again.</p>
            <p>To which I anſwer that if a Man reaps no Benefit by the reception of the Holy Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, the fault is altogether his own; becauſe either he does not duly prepare himſelf for it, or elſe does not receive it ſo often as he ſhould. Some bodies are ſo diſtempered, and ſtomachs vitiated, that they turn the beſt Food into corrupt and evil Nouriſhment: And if a Man of the moſt healthy Conſtitution ſhould
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:64680:18"/> eat but one Meal in a Week, it would never keep him in health and ſtrength. But let the Stomach be cleanſed, and the Body brought into good order; and then let the Man eat his conſtant and daily meals; and he ſhall find both his health and ſtrength encreaſe upon him. And the Caſe is juſt the ſame with this Spiritual Food, which is exhibited to us in the Holy Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament. Whil'ſt the Soul is polluted and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtempered with Sins unrepented of, it will cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly rather do us hurt than good to receive it: And when Men partake of it but once in a year or two, or, it may be, not ſo often; whatever ſtrength or refreſhment their Souls begin to find thereby, is loſt and forgot before it comes again to be renewed by the ſame ordinance. But let a Man throughly cleanſe and purge his Soul from Sin by a ſincere repentance; and with an honeſt heart, and mind well prepared, let him come as often as he can to God's Holy Table; and by the frequent and conſtant uſe of this Holy Sacrament, he need not doubt but he ſhall find himſelf continually to grow more and more in Grace; becoming ſtill better and better enabled to reſiſt all temptations, and daily finding more and more quiet, and comfort, in his mind and conſcience.</p>
            <p>And thus much for the Fourth impediment.</p>
            <p>I come now, in the Laſt place, of all to ſpeak a word or two to thoſe who are not well Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied with the manner of celebrating the Holy Communion in our Church, and therefore will not join with our congregations in it.</p>
            <p>Two things there are, which they chiefly ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject againſt us in this caſe: One that we make
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:64680:18"/> uſe of ſuch Ceremonies as they cannot comply with; and in particular, that the holy Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion is amongſt us to be received in the poſture of Kneeling: And the other is that we admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter it to a mixt congregation, without a ſtrict enquiry into the qualifications of all thoſe who are admitted to it.</p>
            <p>To the firſt of theſe I anſwer that no man can ſay that either Kneeling at the Holy Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or any other of the Rites or Ceremonies which we uſe at the celebration of it, are Sinful or unlawful; becauſe it does not appear that God has any where <hi>Forbid</hi> them. The utmoſt then that they can pretend, is only that they are improper, and inconvenient. Now, beſides that others, who may be as good Judges, are of a different opinion; I would deſire to know whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſuch things as are not Sinful, but only im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proper and inconvenient, can be a ſufficient warrant to any Man to ſeperate himſelf from the Communion of an Orthodox, Eſtabliſhed Church? If not; then they have no juſt reaſon up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this account to ſeparate from us. But if they be, then I would farther demand, which is the greateſt inconveniency, to kneel at the Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, or to make a Schiſm in the Church? And of the two inconveniences whether we ought not alwaies to make choice of the leaſt?</p>
            <p>To the other objection I anſwer, that where any Man openly appears to be wicked and ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalous in his Life and converſation; By the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcipline of our Church, we are required to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude ſuch a Perſon from the Holy Communion, untill he gives good evidence of his repentance and reformation. But where nothing outwardly
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:64680:19"/> appears againſt a Man, who lives in the profeſſion of the true Religion; what have we to do to enquire into the ſecrets of his Heart, for which he is accountable only to God? And if our Saviour Chriſt did not exclude even <hi>Judas</hi> himſelf from the Holy Communion, becauſe, at that time, he had done nothing openly; altho Chriſt well knew that he had made a private agreement with the cheif Prieſts to betray him; Why ſhould we take upon us to be more ſtrict in this matter? Or who has given us any Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority ſo to be?</p>
            <p>And thus have I Examined, and I hope ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently Anſwered, all the Pretences which Men do ordinarily make for neglecting the Holy Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion. I have but this one thing to add, and I have done; namely, that as it is a great Sin to receive the Holy Communion unworthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that is to ſay without true Repentance; ſo certainly is it no leſs a Sin, to ſlight and neglect that Ordinance, which Chriſt himſelf has expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly appointed and commanded, in remembrance of that Death and Paſſion which he under went for us. Let us therefore take the matter into our ſerious conſideration; and whileſt we are ſo very cautious to avoid the danger on the one hand; let us not be ſo fooliſh as to run our ſelves into as great a hazard on the other. For as he who preſumed to come to the Nuptial Feaſt; without <hi>a Wedding Garment,</hi> was ſeverely pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed for his Preſumption, <hi>Matt.</hi> 22. 13. So they who neglected to come at all, and ſlighted the invitation which was given them, were ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted as unworthy Perſons, and received their doom accordingly: <hi>v.</hi> 7. 8.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:64680:19"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
